<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vvhisper in the eare of Mr. Thomas Edwards minister. By VVilliam VValwyn marchant. Occasioned by his mentioning of him reproachfully, in his late pernitious booke, justly entituled the Gangræna.</title>
            <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W694</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E328_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200666</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861346</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861346</idno>
            <idno type="VID">159597</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97110)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 159597)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 53:E328[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vvhisper in the eare of Mr. Thomas Edwards minister. By VVilliam VValwyn marchant. Occasioned by his mentioning of him reproachfully, in his late pernitious booke, justly entituled the Gangræna.</title>
                  <author>Walwyn, William, 1600-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1-8, 1, 6-7, 4-5, 2-3, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed according to order, by Thomas Paine, for VVilliam Ley, at Paules-Chaine,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>The page after 8 is numbered "1".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 13 1645".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Freedom of religion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:159597:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>VVHISPER</hi> IN THE EARE of Mr. <hi>Thomas Edwards</hi> Miniſter.</p>
            <p>By <hi>VVilliam VValwyn</hi> Marchant. Occaſioned by his mentioning of him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfully, in his late pernitious booke, juſtly entituled the <hi>Gangraena.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Micah. 7.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The good man is periſhed out of the earth, and there <hi>is</hi> none righteous among men: they all lie in wait for blood: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man hunteth his brother with a net.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR,</hi> Your extream fury in driving on a work where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no charitable well minded Chriſtian takes any comfort, but rather an abundance of griefe, hath made me to conclude, that you are quite deaf ou the right chriſtian eare; deaf to all that is good: a man (I fear) altogether without Conſcience, or ſence of goodneſſe: and that you have the uſe of hearing on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on the left ſide of <hi>Machiavilian</hi> policy: juſt as <hi>Demetrius</hi> the ſilver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, that oppoſed not the doctrine of <hi>Chriſt</hi> out of zeale to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſe <hi>Diana</hi> as he pretended: nor out of any hatred to that doctrine, but as it tended to the loſſe of his craft and gain: even ſo you, (as I verily fear) do not indeavour to make odious the ſeverall doctrines and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of conſcienſoious people, out of true zeal to any thing you appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend as truth; or out of hatred to any thing you apprehend as error; but becauſe the doctrines and practices of thoſe you term independants.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:159597:2"/>
Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Antinomians, and Seekers: do all tend to the loſſe of your craft and gain: in that they all diſallow of tythes, as cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious and popiſh, and all contracted for, or enforced maintenance for miniſters under the Goſpel, as diſagreeing to the rule thereof: nay you have further cauſe againſt them, for they ſpoile you not onely of your gaine, but of your glory and domination, things dearer to you then your life: of your glory, in denying your miniſtry to be ſucceſſive from the Apoſtles: of your domination, by denying unto you any more authority to judge of doctrines or diſcipline, then any other ſort of Chriſtian men: and to ſpeak truly, theſe are ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> temptations to ſuch worldly minds as yours, who in your hopes had made your ſelves ſure of the greateſt part of all that was taken from the Prelats, and thereby of a foundation of advancing the honour, and ſplendour, and power, and profit of the Clergy once more in this Nation: It is confeſt that ſuch provocations as theſe have not onely produced ſuch reviling accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as you bring againſt conſcientious well minded people, but a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the calumniators: as it befell the late Prelates, whoſe railing, reviling, and moleſting of the harmeleſſe faithfull puritan, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of heriſie, ſchiſme, faction, ſedition, and the like, being all contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to every mans knowledge and experience of them: the iſſue was, the utter extirpation of their calumniators: and that ſo lately, as might be a warning to you, and ſuch politique worldly men as you are; but that it is (through the wiſdom and juſtice of God) the fate of policy and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique men not to be warned by other mens judgements, but to truſt ſo much to the ſtrength of their braines, that they fear not to trace thoſe very ſteps that gradatim brought the laſt Arch-biſhop to the block, making no conſcience of vexing, diſgraceing and undoing of any man, nay thouſands of men and families, ſtanding twixt them and their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ends: and this too ſo madly and raſhly, as to make themſelves ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries of ſuch, as really aimed at their good, and to preſerve them from thoſe precipitations their folly and malice labours to haſten. And this is your caſe with me, for I am confident and well aſſured, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all thoſe whom in this your frantick booke you have named, there is not one that oppoſed your waies more out of love, and ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly for your good, then I have done: for what ever you through want of an experimentall knowledge of me, or upon miſ-report may judge of me, I am one that do truly and heartily love all mankind, it being the unfeigned deſire of my ſoul, that all men might be ſaved, and come to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:159597:2"/>
the knowledge of the truth, it is my extream grief that any man is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted, moleſted, or puniſhed, and cannot but moſt earneſtly wish, that all occaſion were taken away: there is no man weake, but I would ſtrengthen; nor ignorant, but I would informe: not erronious, but I would rectifie, nor vicious, but I would reclaim, nor cruel, but I would moderate and reduce to clemency: I am as much grieved that any man ſhould be ſo unhappy as to be cruel or unjuſt, as that any man ſhould ſuffer by cruelty or injuſtice: and if I could I would preſerve from both, and however I am miſtaken, it is from this diſpoſition in me, that I have engaged my ſelf in any publick affairs, and from no other, which my manner of proceeding in every particular buſines wherein I have in any meaſure appeared, will ſufficiently evince, to all that have with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out partiallity obſerved me: I never propoſed any man for my enemy, but injuſtice, oppreſſion, innovation, arbitrary power, and cruelty, where ever I found them, I ever oppoſed my ſelf againſt them; but ſo, as to deſtroy the evil, but to preſerve the perſon: and therefore all the war I have made (other then what my voluntary and neceſſary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution hath maintained, which I wiſh ten thouſand times more then my ability, ſo really am I affected with the Parliaments iuſt cauſe for the common freedom of this Nation) I ſay all the war I have made, hath been to get victory on the underſtandings of men: accompting it a more worthy and profitable labour to beget friends to the cauſe I lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, rather then to moleſt mens perſons, or confiſcate eſtates: and how many true and thorow converts have been made through my endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours: you tempt me to boaſt, were I addicted to ſuch a vanity, or were I not better pleaſed with the conſcience of ſo doing. Before this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I was of full years to be ſenſible of the oppreſſion of the times, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now forty five years of age, having accuſtomed my ſelf to all kinds of good reading, and to the conſideration of all things; but ſo, as for a long time I took not boldneſſe to iudge, but upon the approbation of ſome authors and teachers that had captivated my underſtanding both in things morall, politique, and religious: in the laſt of which, being ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſerious and ſincere in my application of things to my own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, my grounds being bad, though much applauded, I found much diſconſolation therein, great uncertainty, and at laſt extream affliction of mind, the law and Goſpel fighting for victory in me, in which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict, the Scriptures were taken in more ſingly, and void of gloſſe, to my aſſiſtance, by the cleare light whereof, I ſaw the enemies I feared van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159597:3"/>
which wrought a real thankfulnes in me towards <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which increaſed with the increaſings of faith: inſomuch as I ſet my ſelf daily more and more to do his will and that in a more publick way then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly: Whereupon an occaſion being offered by this honourable Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, our miniſter and pariſh <hi>(James Garlick-hill London)</hi> being quite out of order: I, with others, moved for reformation, in doing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of how I laboured to have preſerved the continuance and well being of our miniſter: himſelf, and the ancient that, oppoſed out endeavours, I preſume will teſtifie, but if they ſhould not, there is enow that will, but he was a man that truſted to policy, which in the end failed him: our next indeavours were for the whole ward, wherein after much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, we ſo prevailed, that the well affected carryed the choice of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman and common-councell men and all other officers in the Ward: my next publike buſineſſe was with many others, in a remonſtrance to the Common Councell, to move the Parliament to confirm certain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible maximes of free Government: wherein the power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was plainly diſtinguiſhed from the Kings Office, ſo plainly, that had it taken effect: few men after due conſideration thereof, would through error of iudgement have taken part againſt the Parliament, or have befriended arbitrary power, as too too many did for want of light: but it was ſtifled in the birth. I was alſo interreſſed in all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of <hi>Salters</hi> hall, whence much good iſſued to the whole City and Kingdom; where (I beleeve it will be teſtified by all, I was never heard or obſerved to propoſe or ſecond a bad motion, nor far ſhort of any in proſecution of any thing that was good: and when the common enemy was at the higheſt, and the Parliaments forces at the loweſt, I with many others petitioned the Parliament for the generall raiſing and arming of all the well affected in the Kingdom, and though that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo took not its proper effect, and came not to perfection: yet it mated the common enemy, and ſet all wheels at work at home, was the ſpring of more powerfull motions and good ſucceſſes: God ſo ordering things that no man moves for good, but good in one kind or other comes thereof: and in all that I have at any time done, I ever aſſociated my ſelf with perſons of known good affections to Parliament and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: that it is my extream wonder that any well-affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould affirm me to be a man dangerous: I have never ſhunned the light, all that I have had a hand in hath come to the publick view and touch, and truly there hath not been a iuſt thing promoted or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159597:3"/>
to be promoted, that ever I was abſent from, if I had a call there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, and whereas I have addicted my ſelfe to know and underſtand all the ſeverall doctrines and waies of worſhip that are extant, and for that end have taken liberty to hear and to obſerve all: it is that I might be able to iudge rightly of their differences, to vindicate them when they are wronged: and to adviſe them for their good: in doing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I have gained much good, there being not any (how light eſteeme ſoever you make of them) but have ſomthing worthy the obſervation: and this I muſt teſtily for all ſorts of them, they are a people the moſt ready to render love for love, that ever I met withall: and not apt to render evil for evil: they are all univerſally faithfull to the Parliament, friends to all juſt government, and enemies to all unjuſt: but yet there is not any thing I have obſerved that hath prevailed with me to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the publike miniſtry, or the parochial congregations &amp; I have yet ſome hopes to ſee them reduced into ſuch a condition, as that all things thereunto belonging, may without difficulty be juſtified: but though I am not in fellowſhip with thoſe good people you call ſectaries, yet I joyn heart and hand with them in any thing that I judge to be right: and tending to the publike good: and love them as heartily as thoſe that are one with me in iudgement: ſometimes I conteſt with them ſomewhat vehemently in arguing, but it is as I conceive for truth, and for their good: and they take it ſo, and bear with me as I with them: and we meet and part in love, as becometh Chriſtians, nor doth this hinder, but that when any difference befalleth betweene them and the publick miniſters, but that I iudge as clearly in ſuch caſes, as if I had no difference with them, for I eſteem it a high part of true religion to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote common iuſtice: and not to be a reſpecter of perſons in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein the Scripture is my rule: and that being on their ſide, I ſhould take part with them therein againſt my father, miniſter, or the deareſt friend I have in the world: and from hence it is, that when the queſtion is about liberty of Conſcience, the Scripture tells me, every one ought to be fully perſwaded in his own mind, and that whatſoever is not of faith, is ſin: it tells me I muſt doe as I would be done unto: I would not be enforced to the Pariſh Congregations, then I muſt not force them to them, or from their owne: God onely perſwades the heart: compulſion and enforcement may make a confuſed maſſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling hypocrites, not a Congregation of beleevers, that ſeeing our Saviour reproached not thoſe that denyed the reſurrection, angels and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159597:4"/>
ſpirits, nay <hi>Joh.</hi> 12.47.48. &amp;c. he ſaith plainly (and that by authority from heaven, v 49.) <hi>He that refuſeth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that iudgeth him: the word that I have ſpoken, it ſhall iudge him in the laſt day.</hi> Alſo in <hi>Luke</hi> the 9.54.55.56. Inſomuch as I ſee no more war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant now to reproach or puniſh any man for Religion, but rather that we are all bound in peace and love to reclaime our brother from what wee iudge an error in his way: wherein the beſt and moſt knowing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men in our daies, may be miſtaken; being all liable to take truth for error, and error for truth, and therefore there is no cauſe of ſtrife or compulſion, except for maſtery: then which (as I conceive) nothing is more unchriſtian, nevertheleſſe I may ſee a neceſſary uſe of a publick miniſtry, and pariſh Congregations, and it is my work to perſwade o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers therein, and not to ſpeak reproachfully thereof, as they would not have their way reproached: but then when the queſtion is concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a maintenance for theſe publick miniſters: and that any ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt for tythes, or an enforced maintenance, truly in this caſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture manifeſting to my underſtanding, tythes to be ceremoniall and Jewiſh, and ſo to ceaſe at the comming of Chriſt: and that to enforce or enioyn a maintenance though under any other notion, is as I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend contrary to the rule and practice of the Apoſtles, how is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble but I muſt adhere to them therein: but then that our publick mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould have no maintenance, therein I wholy diſſent, and as it hath been my endeavour to aſſiſt the one party to avoid the moleſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their concſciences in tythes, &amp; all enforced contributions ſo have I often propoſed a way for the maintenance of the publick miniſters, more certain, more quiet for themſelves, and leſſe itkſome to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, leſſe diſturbant to the Common-wealth: and thus you may ſee how through miſ-information: you have taken me for an enimy, that have alwaies approved my ſelf your reall friend in all things I apprehended iuſt: and thus you may ſee how dangerous a man I have been that in all theſe publick differences have done no man hurt by word or deed: nay at all the meetings I have frequented, whether at Salters hall, the wind mill, or elſe-where, I never heard any man named reproachfully, but I openly ſhewed the unfitnes thereof: alwaies adviſing that if any man had ought againſt any particular perſon, that he ſhould make it known to thoſe that by law had aright to take notice thereof, and that we ſhould be very cautious in thinking evil of any man upon report and hearſay, eſpecially of any in authority: The truth is, I have been and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159597:4"/>
am of opinion, that it is not good for the Common-wealth, that the miniſters ſhould have any power or iuriſdiction put into their hands, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that it were good for the miniſters themſelves, the ſame having ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten proved their ruine, and the diſturbance of the people, but do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it more ſafe for them, and more for the quiet of the people, that they be freed from all other employments, except preaching and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the publick worſhip of God, according as the Parliament ſhall ordain, for I look upon you as miniſters ordained by the State, and ſo are to do as they conceive is moſt agreeable to the word of God, and moſt beneficiall to the generallity of the people in ſetling whereof, you may adviſe, but are not to urge or be importunate for more power then they ſee good, and it leſſe beſeems you to grow paſſionate, and to move others to be importunate, and by preaching and printing to labour to make their faithfull friends odious unto them, and to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie your deſires, above their own intentions, and ſo to beget emulations and parties, threaten iudgements and deſertions, and turning the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures againſt them and all others that oppoſe or fulfill not your will, as if they were oppoſers of the will of God, which you take upon you to know, with the ſame confidence as the biſhops and prelates did, and in the very ſame manner, and application of Scripture. No interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was good but theirs, no miniſters the miniſters of Chriſt, but whom they ordeyned by impoſition of hands, no government, diſcipline, or worſhip, agreeable to the Scriptures, but theirs, no opinion ſound, but what they allowed, all were ſectaries and hereticks, whom they pleaſed ſo to denominate: thoſe that oppoſed them were ſeditious: diſturbers of the peace, a viperous brood, enemies to the ſtate, and ſubverters of all order and government, and by all means to be extirpated: if any plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded conſcience, they conclude them obſtinate, and thus it is with you expreſly, ſo as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> is indeed but a new edition of Prelaticall doctrine, with ſome additions appliable to the preſent times, and his Clergies immediate intereſt: but truſt me, this is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly preiudiciall to your party, for there is no moderate Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian that can excuſe this, and hath beene a hindrance to me in arguing for a publick miniſtry, beſides you ſoar ſo high in dating expreſſions, as if you preſumed upon ſome other way of obtaining your deſires, then by allowance of Parliament, which may looſe you many friends there, and occaſion them to think they have through a miſtaken com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, foſtered a frozen ſnake in their boſomes, that no ſooner finds
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:159597:5"/>
heat and ſtrength, but falls into his ſerpentine hiſſing, and ſtinging his preſerver, you have alſo loſt many of your friends abroad, by this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian nominating men and women in your <hi>Gangraena,</hi> and many more you will looſe, when they ſhall conſider that you have not taken the known Goſpel way of firſt admoniſhing of them, but upon bare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, as it were to poſt them reproachfully to the view of the world, they cannot deem this as the proceeding of a miniſter of Chriſt, but rather as a violent haſt to do your owne work: truſt me, <hi>I</hi> cannot but impute the great abatement of your ſect, the falling from you of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny iudicious perſons, and the daily great increaſe of othes ſects, to no one thing more, then to your inconſiderate raſhnes, violent railing, and adventuring on unheard of waies to compaſſe your ends, for when <hi>I</hi> have prevailed with ſome (through debate and argument) to come to out publike Churches, and to hear your ſermons, they have found there ſuch abundance of paſſion, ſweat, and labour, not to beget chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren unto Chriſt, by preaching the ſincere Goſpel of Chriſt, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile and reproach, and make odious conſcientious well affected people, becauſe of difference in iudgement, whereby they have been much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from frequenting thoſe places, affirming that all the accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you bring againſt others, are expreſly and viſibly due to your ſelves if but indifferently weighed: as where you charge others with pride, ambition, covetuouſnes, effeminacy, obſtinacy, cruelty, delicacy of pallate, and the like; they have demanded of me with a poſitive vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, whether theſe were not to be found in you, rather then in thoſe you have condemned for thoſe vices, blaming me very much for going about to excuſe the ſame, inſomuch as <hi>I</hi> verily beleeve, you have no e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy like your ſelf, and am perſwaded if you would forſake all corrupt intereſts, and would conſcienſciouſly ſet your ſelfe to do the worke of Chriſt, to labour in his word and Goſpel, out of a pure mind, and not for filthy lucre, if you would make it evident by your actions, that you ſeek not ours, but to win us to God, that you would thereby prevaile more in one halfe year towards your owne comfortable eſtabliſhment, then you ſhall in an age by all your by-waies and policies, therefore leave them, and betake your ſelf to the work of Chriſt, whilſt it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to day: the night of ignorance <hi>I</hi> preſume is paſt with you: O that truth and this my plain dealing might beget or awaken Conſcience in you, and provoke you to caſt of the works of darknes, and to put on the armour of light, and henceforth to walk honeſtly and not in ſtrife and
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:159597:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
envying, but to walk in love as Chriſt hath loved nor is it meet you ſhould eſteeme your ſelf a Chriſtian, untill you find your ſoul poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the ſpirit of true Chriſtian love, which doth no evil to his neighbour, and therefore is the fullfilling of the Law. What though you could prevail (as you endeavour) to work the ruine of all that oppoſe your iudgement or ends? Would it be peace in the latter end? no, aſſure your ſelf it would be a ſulphurious bitterneſſe and horror of conſcience, and therefore ſit downe and ſeriouſly conſider what you are reſolved to do, weigh your intentions in the even ſcales of love, touch and prove them with the touch ſtone of love, if you would be eſteemed a diſciple of Chriſt, it muſt bee knowne by love: now love ſuffereth long, and is kind; boaſteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up, doth not behave it ſelfe unſeemly, ſeeketh not her owne, is not provoked to anger, it thinketh not evil, it rejoyceth not in iniquity, but reioyceth in the truth: beareth all things, beleeveth all things, hopeth all things, endureth all things, this is that <hi>I</hi> would ever whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in your ear, this being a balſame that often, and well rub'd in, may Cure your <hi>Gangraen,</hi> and though at firſt your diſtermper may cauſe you to loath it, yet take a little and a little of it, uſe inwardly and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, conſtantly, and you will find your diſpoſition to alter and change from one degree unto another, until you come to be a ſtrong and healthfull Chriſtian: of <hi>Saul</hi> a perſecutor, you will become <hi>Paul</hi> a preacher of peace and reconciliation by Jeſus Chriſt, and bee able to lay down your life for thoſe Brethren you have ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed: then will you do as you would be done unto, and in all things diſputable allow every one to be fully perſwaded in their own minds, and then you will bee ſencible, that <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſinne:</hi> you will acknowledge it is God only that can perſwade the heart, and (doing your duty) patiently waite his leiſure for the converſion of your Brethren: the ſame mind and meeknes will bee in you, as was in Chriſt Jeſus, and you will be mercifull as our heavenly Father is mercifull: you will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king flax; then you will ſee what pure religion and undefiled before God, even the Father, is: you will feed the hungry, cloath the naked, viſit the ſick, relieve the priſoner, deliver the captive, and ſet the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed free, eſpecially the oppreſſed for Conſcience ſake: you will then ſee error in judgement or miſapprehenſion in worſhip, to bee but a mote in your brothers eye, compared to a perſecuting or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſting,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:159597:6"/>
or the reproaching beame in your owne: in a word, would you ſeriouſly ſet your ſelfe to the ſtuddy and practice of love, you would againe fill your Churches, and without the help of Jewiſh Tythes, or any unchriſtian or forced maintenance, preaching the Goſpel, would live comfortably of the Goſpel and draw all men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe blemiſhes you labour by your <hi>Gangreen</hi> to ſtick upon mee, I beleeve your labour will be loſt, except in the opinion of ſuch as know me not: but to acquit my ſelfe farther, and to free them from prejudice, to what I have ſaid I add thus much more.</p>
            <p>In your 96. page, you have me in theſe uncharitable expreſſions, one Mr. <hi>Walwyn</hi> a ſeeker, and a dangerous man, a ſtrong head: truely in the mind you were in, when you wrote this <hi>Gangreen,</hi> I am hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily glad I appeared not worthy of your Commendations, certainly you have been extreamly covetous of informations, you ſeeme to have ſuckt them in with greedineſſe, and ſwallowed them without chewing; tis pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y an evil intent ſhould be better ſerved; your infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations to my knowledge of many particulars as that of Mr. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnes</hi> and others, and my ſelf, have been ſuch to you, as if they had been made of purpoſe to ſhame you to all the world, I a ſeeker good now; whoſe your author? Am I one becauſe I know many, and have been amongſt them often, that I might know them fully; ſo have I been with all other judgements, but I carry with mee in all places a Touch-ſtone that tryeth all things, and labours to hold nothing but what upon plain grounds appeareth good and uſefull: I abandon all nicities and uſeleſſe things: my manner is in all diſputes reaſonings and diſcourſes, to enquire what is the uſe: and if I find it not very materiall, I abandon it, there are plain uſefull doctrines ſufficient to give peace to my mind: direction and comfort to my life: and to draw all men to a conſideration of things evidently uſefull, hath been a ſpeciall cauſe that I have applyed my ſelfe in a friendly manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all: but hence it is that ſome have ſaid I am a great Annabaptiſt, others (upon as good ground) a great Antinomian: and you a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker: miſtake me not, I do not eſteeme theſe as names of reproach, no more then to be called Presbyterian or Independent; nor doe J take upon me peremptorily to determine what is truth, and what is error, amongſt any of them: all have a poſſibility of error: I judge all Conſcienſcious, and to hold their ſeverall judgements upon
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:159597:6"/>
grounds of ſcripture: to them appearing, and ſo long cannot but hold them: and why any ſhould controule another, I cannot di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne: had I all the power or ſtrength in the World at my diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in caſes of religion I conceive I ſhould ſinne, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould do more then in a loving way offer my argument, and gently perſwade to what <hi>I</hi> conceive is both evidently true, and really uſefull: and thus have <hi>I</hi> done amongſt thoſe my loving friends, whom you judge ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers: for though I do fully aſſent with them that now in theſe times there is no ſuch miniſtry as the Apoſtles were, endowed with imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate power from on high, by impoſition of whoſe hands, the Holy Ghoſt was conferred, enabling to ſpeak with tongues, and do mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, in a moſt wonderfull manner, and to ſpeake to all men, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible word of God: and that convincingly to the Conſciences of gain ſayers: yet am I not thereby of opinion that we may not make uſe of thoſe things they have left unto us in the ſcriptures of the mind and will of God; or that it is not profitable to follow their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples ſo far as we are able in all things, for what though the effects are now weake, in compariſon of theirs, yet are they ſuch as bring great ſatisfaction with them: I have often perſwaded with them that they ſhould not reject what they may with much comfort make uſe of, becauſe they cannot find what they ſeek, &amp; for ought I know are not like to find in this world: ſee now what a ſeeker you have found of me: I once heard you at Chriſt-Church, which few ſeekers will do, but never but once, for I was not ſo blind a ſeeker, as to ſeek for Grapes of thornes, or Figgs of thiſtles: and why <hi>I</hi> pray you a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous man? indeed, by ſome reall dangerous men, I have been ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſo, ſome whereof are falne into the ſnare they laid for all the well affected in this City; but that ever I was accounted ſo by any that converſed with me, that was a knowing well-affected man, I do not beleeve, and I beleeve I could produce thouſands of knowing well-affected perſons, that if they heare I am engaged, and doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in any publick buſineſſe, though they know no tittle thereof, will adventure odds; it is both juſt and neceſſary, and therefore you incline me to beleeve that you labour for beliefe onely amongſt the weake, ignorant, raſh, or ill affected people, with whom Credit and repute is not worth the having: well, your laſt appellation you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon me is a ſtrong head, and what would you have underſtood by this? Would you have your diſciples ſtand aloof and not dare to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:159597:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:159597:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:159597:8"/>
hold diſcourſe with me, leſt I ſhould open your deſignes, and make it appeare how much it concerns your corrupt interreſt to keep their heads in ignorance and a ſuperſtitious weakneſſe: is it becauſe I know whoſe maxim, this is <hi>Ruſtica gens, optima Flens, peſſima ridens:</hi> Is it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe my hearing is ſo good as not to bee perverted by Gloſing do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, or becauſe my ſmelling ſerves my turne to ſmell a Fox, or Wolfe, though in Sheeps clothing, or is my ſeeing ſo ſtrong that it diſpels the magick miſts of ſophiſticated art: or is it becauſe my taſte diſcerneth the brackiſhneſſe of flattery, from the pure ſweetneſſe of plain dealing: or do you mean head ſtrong, becauſe I am not likely nor could ever be drawn to dance after your Pipe.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe theſe are the cauſes that any ſtrong head troubles you; nevertheleſſe, as ſtrong as it is, you ſee a ſmall knock from your hard hand hath ſo opened it, that I can hardly ſhut it again, but Ile ſhut it preſently, onely thus much, I cannot ſee how authority can paſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this unparaleld uſe of the preſſe which you have taken, to name in publike ſo many of their faithfull adherents in ſo reproachfull a manner; to tax their proceedings in the proceedings of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, to affirme and declare to all the world, that the victorious ſucceſſes of the Parliaments forces, is but the increaſe of errors and heriſies, that ſectaries of all ſorts get places of profit and power, and be the men all in requeſt for offices and employments. in the which, you make your ſelf the iudge of what is error and herſie, and who is a ſectary: in all which you are as likely to be miſtaken as any man: for none are ſuch in your calender, but ſuch (as at firſt I told you) who ſtand twixt you and your profit, glory and domination: ſo as a man may be a reall good Chriſtian, and a moſt cordiall friend to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and nevertheleſſe be exploded by you for a ſectary, or an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick: one thing more, you, and ſuch as you are (if you be not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſince you wrote your <hi>Gangraena,</hi> as I heartily wiſh you were) doe extreamly abuſe this Nation, in laying the main weight of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (intended) upon the reduceing of mens judgements and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in. Religion to union and uniformity, whereas the main weight of all reſteth, in extirpating the popiſh prelaticall ſpirit of perſecution and moleſtation for conſcience. as the main thing that oppreſſed all ſorts of conſcientious people before the Parliament, and ſince; and that which cannot fail to diſturbe and vex any nation where it remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, but the truth is, without it you cannot keep your ſelf aloſt: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:159597:8"/>
it you cannot compell a maintenance: diſtinguiſh a Clergy, nor have power over mens perſons by their conſciences, but grant you the power you deſire, and you are maſter of all, and then ſee who dares open his mouth, or move his pen in this argument: your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent confidence proceeds from the miſt you have raiſed, but it is not yet thick enough, nor will our engliſh braynes prove ſo muddy as to afford matter for thickning, I beleeve and hope it is now at thickeſt, and when your hopes are greateſt, you will find your ſelf in a fogge: to hold men in ignorance or bondage is not a work either for honeſt men or good-Chriſtians, but abhorred by both, and beleeve it, truth is become too ſtrong to admit of either in this age: and we truſt the honourable Parliament that are choſen to preſerve us from both, will not fail to preſerve us, though you ſhould do the worſt you can, and whereas you commend them to the love of God and his truth, and the hating of all ſects and ſchiſmes, I in all humility and true love to all that honour God, and deſire the welfare of England, do moſt heartily pray, that they may hate all perſecuting ſects with a perfect hatred: all enforcing and compulſive ſchiſmaticks, as the onely cauſe of all trouble and diſtraction.</p>
            <p>To conclude, If you be ſo ill as your word, and bring forth ſuch evill fruit once every month, and that we whoſe names you have bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, can find a licencer, (as we hope we ſhall) that will do but ſo much for Chriſt, as yours hath done for <hi>B.</hi> We ſhall I doubt not, find a new way of innocculation, and produce grapes out of your thorns, and figges out of your thiſtles, and fetch abundance of good out of your evil: but more happy will it be for you if you repent, (once a month ſhall I ſay) once every houre, and in token thereof, uſe your uttermoſt indeavour to promote this or the like petition to the honourable Parliament, whereby you will make ſome amends for the evill you have done by this your book.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <opener>Humbly ſheweth,</opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat as with all thankfulnes we acknowledge your unwearied labours to remove the grievances and dangers of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, ſo are we exceedingly grieved to obſerve the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold unexpected difficulties which at ſeverall times have obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted your proceedings, amongſt which we conceive the differences in Religion to be the greateſt, and of moſt importance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:159597:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In your conſiderations whereof, being an affair of ſo tender a nature, ſo apt to be miſ-underſtood, and ſuch as hath miſcarried in all former Parliaments, to the great diſturbance of this Nation, and to the great affliction of conſcientious people, we humbly conceive you have not in any thing ſhewed greater regard to the glory of God or greater care of the welfare of the people, then in proceeding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with ſo cautious and adviſed a deliberation: giving time and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to your wiſedoms, rightly to underſtand the word of God in that point which moſt concerneth tender conſciences, to hear, try and examine all that can or may be ſaid or writ thereof, and we truſt you will in the end produce that which ſhall be agreeable to the will and mind of God, and to the quiet of all wel-affected people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And although your progreſſe therein hath not been with ſo much ſpeed, or ſuch ſev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rity towards tender Conſciences, as ſome impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunely have deſired, yet have we good cauſe to beleeve that you have been guided thoreinby the good hand of God, who in due time will (we doubt not) bring you to ſuch an iſſue, as neither your ſelves, nor any others (well minded) ſhall have cauſe to repent, or ever to alter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And therefore we most earnestly intreat that you will not through any importunity be induced to haſten your proceedings in this weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty cauſe (wherein the leaſt error may prove very prejudiciall) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what upon your mature deliberation ſhall appeare to be juſt and neceſſary: there being as we humbly conceive, no greater breach of the priviledge or abatement of the power of Parliament, then for any to do more then humbly to informe or adviſe you in this, or any other negotiation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed be God though the differences are many in point of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment throughout your quarters, as they have been alwaies through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the world, and will be ſo long as knowledge is imperfect: yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing amongſt conſcionable, quiet, well affected people, they are not properly to be called diviſions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:159597:9"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And though we cannot but fear there are ſome wicked Polititi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans that endeavour by all means to make them ſuch, and thereby to diſtemper and diſtract all your undertakings, and to make the ſame advantagious to their unjuſt ends, yet are we confident (through Gods protection) their endeavours ſhall be fruitleſſe (except to draw confuſion on themſelves) God having bleſſed the people in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall with a cooler ſpirit, and greater wiſdom, then by dividing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, or not adhering unto you, to become a prey to any enemy; and hath produced univerſally in them, as in us your humble Petitioners, a reſolution to defend the juſt power and priviledge of this honourable Houſe, againſt all deluſion or oppoſition whatſoever, to the laſt penny of our eſtates, or laſt drop of our bloods, beſeeching you to go on with the ſame caution and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſolution, to perfect thoſe juſt works you have undertaken, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as God ſhall direct you, both for the manner and the ſeaſon: for his way is beſt, and his time moſt ſeaſonable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>And as in duty bound, we ſhall ever pray, &amp;c.</closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>To conclude, if you ſhall do this conſcionably and effectually, I am confident henceforward you will not be able to do any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth, but for the truth which is the unfeigned deſire of him who cannot but earneſtly deſire your reformation, and eternall happineſſe:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Walwyn.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
